A Guide to the Hugh H. Smith Papers FA036
Rockefeller Archive Center
Hugh H. Smith papers
1927-1988
Rockefeller Archive Center
Smith, Hugh Hollingsworth
Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division
Rockefeller Foundation
FA036
3.04 Cubic Feet 8 letter document cases
Scope and Contents
Important subjects in this collection include arbovirus research, encephalitis, International Health Division, microbiology, public health, Rockefeller Foundation reorganizations, Rockefeller Foundation virus labs, tick fever, tuberculosis, and yellow fever.
Among the correspondents are Richard Anderson, Marston Bates, Henry Beeuwkes, George Bevier, H. R. Carter, Wilbur Downs, John Ferrell, Lewis Hackett, J. G. Harrar, Rolla Hill, Wilson Jameson, Edwin Lennette, Dean Rusk, F. F. Russell, W. A. Sawyer, Hugh H. Smith, G. K. Strode, Richard Taylor, Andrew Topping, Thomas Turner, Andrew J. Warren, B. E. Washburn, John Weir, and Telford Work.
Biographical / Historical
Hugh Hollingsworth Smith was born in Easley, South Carolina, on December 12, 1902. He received an A.B. degree from Davidson College in 1923, an M.D. from Johns Hopkins University in 1927, and an M.P.H. from Johns Hopkins School of Hygiene and Public Health in 1935.
From 1920-1930 Dr. Smith was an Instructor in Medicine at the University of Rochester. He became a special member of the International Health Division of The Rockefeller Foundation in 1930 and from 1931-1934, Dr. Smith conducted tuberculosis studies in Kingston, Jamaica. He worked in the yellow fever labs in Brazil during 1937-1938 and in Colombia in 1938-1941. In 1941 he was appointed a member of the Rockefeller Health Commission and was attached to the London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine. During his time in London he was a member of the Tropical Advisory Committee on Medical Service and Supplies of the Allied Postwar Requirements Bureau, served as liaison for the British Colonial Office in connection with the development of public health programs in the British West Indies and Africa and was involved in nutritional studies for the war effort.
In 1944 Dr. Smith returned to the United States as Assistant Director of the International Health Division and Regional Director for the United States. In 1951 he became Associate Director of the Division of Medical and Public Health and served in that capacity until he retired in 1954.
After his retirement from the Foundation, Dr. Smith moved to Arizona, where he was a professor of microbiology at the University of Arizona. In 1959 he set up a lab at the University for the study of arthropod-borne virus, and in 1961 he was awarded a grant by the National Institute of Health which ran through 1966 for research in arthropod-borne encephalitis in Southern Arizona.
Dr. Smith contributed articles to a variety of medical journals including Arizona Medicine and was a co-author of "Yellow Fever," ed. G. K. Strode, 1951. In 1978 he published his memoirs, "Life's a Pleasant Institution: The Peregrinations of a Rockefeller Doctor." He died in December 1995.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Arrangement
There are three series in the Hugh Smith collection:
Series 1 - 1931-1967 Series 2 - 1927-1988
Series 1020 - Photographs
File Plan
Former Classification: IV 2A 11
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The papers of Hugh H. Smith were first deposited with The Rockefeller Foundation Archives in June 1968, by Hugh H. Smith. Later additions were received by The Rockefeller University as a gift from Dr. Smith in 1987 and 1988.
Public health; Biology -- Research; Medical research; Tuberculosis; Arboviruses; Yellow fever; Microbiology; Encephalitis
- 1931-1967, 1
  Scope and Contents
  Within Series 1, there are two groupings of material: the Rockefeller Foundation group and the virus group. The Rockefeller Foundation group consists of material which pertains to Dr. Smith's formal association with the Foundation and his correspondence with members of the Foundation after he retired. Correspondence forms the bulk of the group but there are also reports and diaries included.
  The Series 1 section on viruses contains material from the Rockefeller virus labs as well as Dr. Smith's own activities in arbovirus research in Arizona. It consists mainly of correspondence. Professional interests note a variety of activities in which Dr. Smith was involved either in his association with the University of Arizona or through his membership in medical and public health organizations.
  Arrangement
  Series 1 is generally chronological in arrangement.
  - Rockefeller Foundation, 1930-1966 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Rockefeller Foundation, 1930-1966 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Rockefeller Foundation, 1930-1966 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Rockefeller Foundation, 1930-1966 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Rockefeller Foundation, 1930-1966 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Rockefeller Foundation, 1930-1966 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Rockefeller Foundation, 1930-1966 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Comments on the Future of the International Health Division (IHD)" (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "Results of Vaccination with Heat-Killed Tubercle Baccili at the Mental Hospital, Kingston, Jamaica. 1931-1934" (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Twenty Years Progress in Health Work in the U.S. 1910-1930" (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Yellow Fever - West Africa, 1921-1934 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Yellow Fever Vaccine (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Diary - A. Mahaffey, February-September 1928 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Diary - W. A. Sawyer, October 1932 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Diary - A. M. Walcott, 1928-1931 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Diary - A. M. Walcott, 1928-1931 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Diary - A. M. Walcott, 1928-1931 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Diary - A. M. Walcott, 1928-1931 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - T. B. Haynes - Death, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Hideyo Noguchi - Death, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Adrian Stokes - Death, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - W. A. Young - Death, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Yellow Fever Reports (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - "Controlling Yellow Fever" (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Yellow Fever - "The Plague Killers" (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Yellow Fever - Bibliography and Abstracts (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - West Africa (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Virus, 1936-1966 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Virus, 1936-1966 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Virus, 1936-1966 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Virus, 1936-1966 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Professional Interests, 1954-1966 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Professional Interests, 1954-1966 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Professional Interests, 1954-1966 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Memberships, 1937-1966 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1947-1967 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1947-1967 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1947-1967 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Christmas Cards (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - History of Microbiology Lecture, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - "Something Curious in the Medical Line", 1963 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Reprints (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - "Life's a Pleasant Institution: The Peregrinations of a Rockefeller Doctor", 1975 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - "A Place to Meet" (Villa Serbelloni), 1968 (Box 4, Folder 44)
- 1927-1988, 2
  The bulk of the material in Series 2 is correspondence, which has a chronological arrangement. The correspondence falls into two broad categories. The first is letters to Dr. Smith from friends and colleagues of The Rockefeller Foundation, the International Health Division, and the scientific community. These are mostly personal but do cover some professional matters. The other category of correspondence is letters between Dr. Smith and his wife, Mary.
  Series 2 also contains two folders of reprints and pamphlets on Dr. Smith's medical and scientific research, two folders of miscellanea from his personal life, and other material documenting his personal and professional interests and activities.
  Series 2 is arranged alphabetically by type of material.
  - Clippings, 1938-1985, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Correspondence - University of Rochester School of Medicine, 1927-1933 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Correspondence - Jamaica, 1933-1936, 1939, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Correspondence - Friends and Associates, 1940-1987, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Correspondence - Friends and Associates, 1940-1987, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Correspondence - Friends and Associates, 1940-1987, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Correspondence - Friends and Associates, 1940-1987, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Correspondence - Hugh and Mary Smith, 1945-1969, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Correspondence - Hugh and Mary Smith, 1945-1969, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Greeting Cards (Box 6, Folder 54)
  - Invitations and Honors, 1931-1944 (Box 6, Folder 55)
  - Memberships, 1937-1963 (Box 6, Folder 56)
  - Military Records, 1943-1946 (Box 6, Folder 57)
  - Miscellanea, n.d., 1927-1958 (Box 6, Folder 58)
  - Miscellanea, 1968-1988 (Box 6, Folder 59)
  - "Notes on the Tucson Society of Tropical Medicine", 1985 (Box 6, Folder 60)
  - Publications and Reprints, 1936-1939, 1941-1985 (Box 6, Folder 61)
  - Publications and Reprints, 1936-1939, 1941-1985 (Box 6, Folder 62)
  - Travel Documents, 1934-1966 (Box 6, Folder 63)
- Hugh H. Smith photographs, 1932-1965; 1020; 0.38 Cubic Feet; Approximately 200 prints
  Biographical / Historical
  Hugh Hollingsworth Smith was born in Easley, South Carolina, on December 12, 1902. He received an A.B. degree from Davidson College in 1923, an M.D. from Johns Hopkins University in 1927, and an M.P.H. from Johns Hopkins School of Hygiene and Public Health in 1935.
  From 1920-1930 Dr. Smith was an Instructor in Medicine at the University of Rochester. He became a special member of the International Health Division of The Rockefeller Foundation in 1930 and from 1931-1934, Dr. Smith conducted tuberculosis studies in Kingston, Jamaica. He worked in the yellow fever labs in Brazil during 1937-1938 and in Colombia in 1938-1941. In 1941 he was appointed a member of the Rockefeller Health Commission and was attached to the London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine. During his time in London he was a member of the Tropical Advisory Committee on Medical Service and Supplies of the Allied Postwar Requirements Bureau, served as liaison for the British Colonial Office in connection with the development of public health programs in the British West Indies and Africa and was involved in nutritional studies for the war effort.
  In 1944 Dr. Smith returned to the United States as Assistant Director of the International Health Division and Regional Director for the United States. In 1951 he became Associate Director of the Division of Medical and Public Health and served in that capacity until he retired in 1954.
  After his retirement from the Foundation, Dr. Smith moved to Arizona, where he was a professor of microbiology at the University of Arizona. In 1959 he set up a lab at the University for the study of arthropod-borne virus, and in 1961 he was awarded a grant by the National Institute of Health which ran through 1966 for research in arthropod-borne encephalitis in Southern Arizona.
  Dr. Smith contributed articles to a variety of medical journals including Arizona Medicine and was a co-author of "Yellow Fever," ed. G. K. Strode, 1951. In 1978 he published his memoirs, "Life's a Pleasant Institution: The Peregrinations of a Rockefeller Doctor." He died in December 1995.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Photographs, slides, and other images are open for scholarly research. RAC is unable to provide access to obsolete media and original digital media. In addition separated media may not yet have undergone stabilization procedures. When feasible, a digital surrogate may be created via special order. All applicable charges will apply.
  Photographs
  - Hugh H. Smith, 1937-1939; 27 prints (Box 6, Folder 51)
    Scope and Contents note
    Vaccinations, diseases, yellow fever, laboratories, Brazil.
  - Hugh H. Smith, 1937-1940; 24 prints (Box 6, Folder 52)
    Yellow fever, diseases, Brazil, laboratories.
  - Hugh H. Smith, 1932-1957; 18 prints (Box 6, Folder 53)
    Yellow fever, Colombia, Jamaica, homes, diseases.
  - Hugh H. Smith, 1933-1965; 16 prints (Box 6, Folder 54)
    Jamaica, diseases, tuberculosis, wards, Egypt, pyramids, Smith family, Colombia, ceremonies.
  - Brazil, 8 prints (Box 6, Folder 55)
    Diseases, yellow fever, Brazil, vaccinations, laboratories.
  - Colombia, 22 prints (Box 6, Folder 56)
    Yellow fever, diseases, laboratories.
  - Egypt, 1 print (Box 6, Folder 57)
    Mosquitos, diseases, field studies.
  - Family, 9 prints (Box 6, Folder 58)
    Smith family, children.
  - Friends and Associates, 13 prints (Box 6, Folder 59)
    Children, parties.
  - India, 3 prints (Box 6, Folder 60)
    Diseases, monuments, Taj Mahal.
  - Jamaica, 6 prints (Box 6, Folder 61)
    Diseases, tuberculosis, Rockefeller Foundation staff, insane asylums.
  - Johns Hopkins University, 13 prints (Box 6, Folder 62)
    Hospitals, schools, staff, Students.
  - Rockefeller Foundation and Related Colleagues, 20 prints (Box 6, Folder 63)
    RF Staff.
  - Hugh H. Smith, 15 prints (Box 6, Folder 64)
    Children, clubs, homes.
  - Uganda, 1 print (Box 6, Folder 65)
    Blood donors.
  - Duplicates, 11 prints (Box 7, Folder 66)
    Yellow fever, diseases, health officials, portraits, group portraits.